To me, that's kind of mind-blowing
because like the base model wasn't
trained on any human data at all.
>> This is Sergey Lavine, one of the
world's leading robotics researchers,
and I asked him all about the current
state of humanoid robotics. What are the
most astonishing emergent capabilities
you've seen so far?
>> I don't think anybody watching that eval
thought that the robot was going to do
this.
>> I have some questions here on China.
There's no avoiding it sometimes.
If humanoid robotics did not succeed in
singledigit years, what do you think
would be the most likely reason why
humanoid robotics failed?
Here's the full episode.
LLMs have caused unprecedented impact
and investment in that area. Physical AI
and humanoid robots could potentially be
even bigger. And so I wanted to ask you
today about where are we today with
humanoid robotics and how do you foresee
this technology actually being deployed
into the world. I guess with machine
learning uh what we've learned over the
last few years over the last decade
rather is that um it works when you do
it at scale and this is like very
obvious now but it wasn't always
obvious. Uh but there's a caveat which
is you have to like scale the right
thing and uh you know initially when
people started working on um models for
language for example the dominant uh
design was uh LSTMs um some people
remember what those are. They were like
kind of okay they were a lot better than
what came before that but they didn't
really scale as well. And then the the
big thing with transformers was not that
transformers were somehow like uh
particularly um you know mathematically
elegant or anything like that. It's just
that they scaled better. So they were
easier to train a very large amounts of
data with lots of parameters. So the
technology proceeds in phases. First you
figure out what you can scale basically
what is the scalable technology and then
you pour on a lot more of kind of an
industrial scale effort adding lots of
data adding to model size and that's
when kind of the magic happens. So when
we're doing kind of more fundamental
technology development the key is to
understand like what are those scalable
levers. So figure out the design, figure
out like roughly the mixtures and and
that by itself does something pretty
cool, but not like uh but that's that's
not the thing that actually changes the
world. It's like when you start pulling
that lever that things actually change.
So with LLMs um when uh like the first
GPT models came out uh with GPT2 like it
did some stuff but it was sort of like
um like a parlor shook, right? So you
you could like get it to synthesize a
story about like unicorns in Peru or
something and it was like coherent
English but it wasn't like a thing that
would solve lots of real world problems.
But the folks that worked on this kind
of recognized that like hey there's
something kind of magical that happens
because uh as you add uh more data and
you make the model bigger like you know
this stuff gets more coherent and more
effective. So they they they could see
that if we do a lot more of that then
it'll become a lot more powerful. So uh
to come back to your question what I
would say about robotics is that it's
not in the in the like GPT4 to GPT5
stage where it's like an industrial
scale effort to kind of make the model
bigger and and u get more capability out
it. It's in that stage where we're
establishing the fundamental
technologies and because of that what uh
one should expect to see right now is
not necessarily that like you know each
month the model gets bigger and more
powerful by some predictable uh kind of
scaling curve. It's that the I guess the
scaling properties themselves are
evolving as we develop the right
technologies. So, uh, to to bring this
back to something like closer to
reality, um, I'm very happy with like
the demos that we're doing here at
physical intelligence, and I think that
a lot of the results that other people
are coming out with are really cool, but
these are to put them in context, we
should not expect these to be the things
that are actually illustrating the power
of scale. We should expect them to be
developing the fundamental technologies
that will be scaled up after that. So,
so where I think we're at now is that
we're actually kind of getting all those
puzzle pieces in place. And I think it's
actually very close. I think a lot of
the puzzle pieces are falling in place.
Uh but it's not like uh what makes it so
hard to prognosticate about where the
technology is going to go is that it's
not yet at that predictable scaling
stage. It's at the stage where we're
figuring out the puzzle pieces, which I
think is really exciting, but it means
that it's also very very hard to foresee
like you know sort of what the
coefficients on that will be.
>> What are the most astonishing emerging
capabilities you've seen so far? that
that is the thing that is the most fun
and and certainly we've seen a a lot
more of that happening as we progress.
Um like you know in the very beginning
it was like it was kind of little things
but they were kind of magical because
you know in robotics basically prior to
like 2024 the stuff like never happened.
Uh so the little things that happen and
this was maybe like at this point about
two years back we would see things like
okay we train our policy for folding
laundry and it takes out like individual
shirts out of the hamper and tries to
fold them and then um um one very vivid
memory I have uh in late 2024 is we we
were watching one of the evals and it
takes out like two shirts at the same
time and I'm I'm watching this I'm like
okay like like it's done for like
there's no way it can possibly do this
and then it puts the two shirts on the
table disentangles and puts one of them
back and then starts folding the other
one. It's like wow like that. Okay, like
in retrospect you can do some like
detective work and figure out where it
got that from some piece of training
data, but that was like one of those
moments where I don't think anybody
watching that eval thought that like the
robot was going to do this. It's like a
little thing. It's like exhibiting the
common sense you expect people to have.
Um but actually the thing that I find
more interesting recently is um uh some
of the mistakes because one of the
things that's uh that was pretty
remarkable about LLMs is that once they
got good enough even the mistakes kind
of made sense in the sense that they
weren't like crazy mistakes where just
outputs like ZZZ all the time but they
were mistakes that sort of semantically
are sensible. Uh we had uh an evaluation
uh last year for pio5 where the robot
was uh uh cleaning up a kitchen and it's
told like put away all the all the
utensils. Like there's like some some
spoons, spatulas, etc. And uh it tries
to open the drawer where it thinks the
silverware goes and it can't get the
drawer open. So it slides over and opens
the oven which is right next to it and
then starts putting this stuff in the
oven. [laughter] It's like, you know,
you can sort of imagine that if you ask
like a child to clean stuff up and put
it away, like they might they might
decide to do that because, okay, it's
like a container and you can put stuff
there and nobody sees it. Um, another
experiment we had is uh uh washing all
the plates. So, it would like pick up
the plates, wash them with a sponge, and
put them on the drying rack. Uh, and uh
this was an experiment on memory because
it has to keep track of everything that
it's doing. It has like a scratch pad
kind of memory where it's writing down
like, hey, you know, I had three plates.
I cleaned the gray one. I cleaned the
green one. And then it drops one of them
on the floor and drives the base over.
so you can't see. I was like, "Okay,
I've cleaned the the gray plate. It's
it's [laughter] done."
Um, so I mean, obviously like these are
not the things that we want to see, but
it's kind of interesting that some of
the mistakes, they're almost like what
you would associate with like a child
trying to do the task. So now now now it
just needs to grow up.
>> You mentioned uh the advancements.
They're kind of happening all over the
industry. And I I know there's a lot of
people building humanoid robots. There's
Figure, there's there's Tesla and
there's many other competitors and you
have the expertise of what is hard and
what isn't. When you look at the
competitors, has there been any
advancement or achievement where you
think, "Oh, that's really admirable and
that's impressive." actually think that
one of the most inspiring things to me
in the industry is to see the um the
kind of takeoff that autonomous driving
systems have had because you know like
one of the criticisms that is sometimes
leveled against robotics researchers is
uh you know it's it's like uh you know
same as like nuclear fusion like it's
it's the technology of the future but
it's always in the future but that's
what people said about autonomous
driving too and now like you know we're
in San Francisco you can go outside you
can take a Whimo and it will actually
like take you to your destination and
there's no driver sitting there So I
like you know without getting too much
into the technical details I think
what's really inspiring about that is
just like this case and point that yes
you can actually have one of these
technologies of the future and it
actually does land and I think it's not
an accident that it's landing now in the
mid 2020s because a lot of the puzzle
pieces for largecale ML are getting to
the level where we can put them together
with like actual physical systems and
there's a lot of differences between
driving and robotic manipulation of
course but I think the illustration that
like yeah we can actually land uh
learning based technologies in the real
physical world I think that's really
inspiring
>> if openthropic
started investing you know more heavily
into robotics how do you think that
would impact the industry do you think
competitors would be you know worried
about that robotics is um is an area
where
maybe to be fair like the ecosystem
hasn't been as healthy as it has in
other areas of machine learning And what
I mean by that is that um like computer
vision and NLP are things that sort of
lend themselves naturally to a machine
learning based ecosystem because there's
freely available data. Uh people kind of
have a a general acceptance that they're
going to be using learning. You know,
there aren't concerns as severe concerns
about like safety, at least physical
safety, right? You know, people
rightfully are concerned about AI
safety, but it's not the same as like a
physical device uh causing some physical
harm. um and uh because of that I think
it's a bit easier to spin up a very
serious large scale ML effort in those
areas. Robotics is not like that.
Robotics traditionally is not a
discipline that um you know really
embraces sharing of data for example. So
I think that the more activity there is
around learning in robotics, the more I
think it'll shift people's thinking
towards this kind of future where we
accept that robots will be controlled by
learned models, not by handdesigned
controllers, that there will be data
that data will need to be shared because
there's no way that somebody can uh
build out a true foundation model in a
single vertical uh and basically kind of
like shift the entire thinking around
robotics to look more like how we think
about vision and NLP as opposed to
traditional factory automation. So I
think in that sense like you know much
as I'm like proud of the work that we're
doing in physical intelligence I think
it'll take more than one company to kind
of like shift every everyone's thinking
in that direction. As a bystander I see
on Twitter these really impressive
demonstrations of Chinese robotics. It
it almost feels like they're ahead in
some sense but I don't have that uh deep
domain expertise. And so I was curious
your thoughts on, you know, what do you
think of China's robotics and, you know,
are are they further along?
>> I think that one thing that um
is very useful and constructive for for
us to do uh those of us that uh work on
these things in the United States and in
Europe, uh is to
ask what is the lesson to learn? And to
me one lesson is that it's important to
have a healthy ecosystem
and ecosystem means that there should be
um you know obviously good researchers,
good engineers working on these things.
there should be like healthy open source
but it also means that the different
industries that contribute to robotics
need to individually be very healthy and
those industries are not just the um you
know computer science ML and and model
building stuff it's also uh supply
chains manufacturing
hardware R&D like these are all very
important things and
aspects of those things are things that
uh the United States does quite Other
aspects of them are things where the
United States has sort of uh you know
let things go a little bit. Uh and I
think that what we should do is we
should look at what's going on in the
world look at the uh some of the uh
excellent results uh that uh Chinese
labs are doing that labs in other
countries are doing and we should take
away that lesson that we should strive
to build a healthier ecosystem and that
means investing in all the different
facets uh that contribute to this. So
you know I'm not like I'm not much of a
business person. I'm not much of a
investment person. So I don't I can't
claim to know how to do this, but I
think that it's important to sort of
fully embrace that this is like a
holistic thing and not something where
we can do just like one piece of it and
like outsource everything else basically
>> of all that the pieces of the ecosystem
are there parts of it as a robotics
researcher in the US if it was better
that would have the biggest impact on
the advancement of robotics? Yeah, I I
think certainly um availability of
reliable lowcost hardware is a big deal
and right now I mean certainly for uh
hardware used for robotics research a
lot of that does come from China and
it's it's good it's uh relatively
inexpensive it's of high quality and uh
meets the uh standards that people
generally need. Uh but it would be
awfully nice to be able to uh source all
that domestically as well. And I I I
don't think there's anything impossible
about that. I think it's just a matter
of sort of uh embracing the fact that
that entire uh ecosystem needs to be
supported rather than just one piece of
it.
>> You can imagine that the lab that is
first to get to scale will be the first
to break out there. There may be this
exponential growth effect where once you
deploy deployment helps you grow faster
and growing faster helps you deploy and
you know this this flywheel and so do
you uh believe that that will happen in
this industry where one lab whether in
US or China will hit some breakout point
and they'll kind of jump everyone else.
>> There is a lot of um uh truth to that. I
think that there's an important detail
to keep in mind. Um the detail is that
um you kind of have to like scale the
right thing. Um so I think that
basically the statement that like the
way that I would phrase this is
having an effective um positive feedback
loop where more deployed robots
translates to more model capability.
That's kind of the key. Uh and like that
that makes total sense. the the trick is
that there are lots of ways that um that
it can be done wrong. So, I'll tell you
like a few obvious ones. Like one
obvious one is um let's say that uh I um
you know I'm a car company and I have a
robotic arm that is welding cars and
it's like there on the uh on the
assembly line and it welds cars every
day and it gets like you know a million
welds every month and so on.
If I just use that as my data flywheel,
I'm unlikely to get something more
capable than a robot that welds cars.
So, since the robot is already there and
it's already welding cars, like
presumably the marginal improvement for
that is not all that valuable. So,
that's an example of how you kind of
have to like scale the right thing
because data is not like um it's not
quite as funible like it's not like uh
electricity or oil. You can't just like
buy more of it. It has to be
heterogeneous. So I I think that
basically it's right but you have to
scale the right thing with the right
technology and the right kind of source
of diverse learning like data is more
like an education program for your robot
than it is a funible commodity.
>> If you think about that data flywheel
and I guess putting out the the proper
platform that would generate data that
matters that would then improve that
platform. When do you first see this
kind of happening in the world? I think
on the technology side like things are
advancing very rapidly towards that and
I think that maybe um a particular
balancing act to strike that would
significantly determine that timeline is
kind of how much structure somebody's
willing to admit. So, you know, on the
one on the one extreme, you could
imagine like jumping straight to fully
unstructured deployment domains like
home robots and that could be really
exciting because then you have a lot of
diversity like right off the bat, but
the bar is a lot higher to uh be
effective enough in that domain to be
safe enough like you know safety is much
bigger issue there because it's around
um uh people in their home. On the other
extreme, you could imagine much more
structured tasks. Maybe not quite the
welding robot, but sort of like, you
know, maybe the robot down the hall that
does something more unstructured, right?
And that could be a much easier domain
in the sense that there's much less uh
safety concerns because it might be
around trained uh humans. Uh the task
might be more uh predictable and so on,
but there is uh um the marginal value of
each bit of data you get in that domain
is lower because there's less variety.
Um, so it's like you could take off
earlier but with a smaller slope or
later but with a larger slope. And you
kind of have to like calibrate that. But
my sense is that whichever end of that
extreme we're talking about, it's in the
uh singledigit years rather than the
double digit years at this point. So it
could be that the more structured ones
might be happening like now or next
year. The less structured ones might be
a few more years out, but probably not
like a decade.
>> A lot of people talk about timelines and
it's kind of more uh nebulous. And I'm
I'm wondering if if you were to put down
a I guess somewhat of a road map, but
not so concrete, but just milestones
towards that north star of
>> robot in my home doing.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's a really good
question. So um maybe to to preface this
answer, I think that there's one thing
that is very important to say about
robotics that is very easy to miss um
from kind of like I guess like the hype
cycle and the demos that people put out,
which is that the the hard thing in
robotics was always um generalization.
But when somebody shows a demonstration
of their system, you know, the
demonstration alone usually doesn't make
it clear what level of generalization is
being shown. the uh highly acrobatic
robot demos for example are really
exciting to look at. But typically if
it's uh something that is like a little
bit more staged like sometimes it's
literally on stage if it's like a show
like you know that that is obviously
like rehearsed and that's okay because
it's like literally just a show but it's
not the same as doing a task every time
reliably in any home. And the
generalization piece often doesn't look
that impressive when viewed in isolation
because generalization is sort of a
property of many trials, not of one
trial. So you might see the robot doing
something fairly mundane and
unimpressive. But what's exciting about
it is that it's doing with an object
that it's never seen before in an
environment that has never been tested
in before. And that's actually harder
than like doing a acrobatic backflip
that it's practiced like a millions of
times. So um with that said uh my answer
to your question is that the road map is
all about both achieving better
generalization and uh kind of that
second order effect of having a
mechanism to get more generalization as
you generalize. So one of the steps on
that road map is to have a very concrete
demonstration of a robotic system that
gets better with autonomous experience
that is collected in in a setting that
it wasn't originally trained for. So I I
do whatever I do on on on the back end,
you know, in the lab in and whatever. I
get my model, I get my uh adaptation
algorithm, I put it in a new setting.
Maybe it's a home, maybe it's a factor,
whatever it is, something where it's
doing something real. uh and it does
okay, but then over time it gets better
and better and it gets better and better
to the point where it reaches sort of
practically relevant levels of
robustness without sort of capping out
at like 50%. Like that I think would be
a major milestone. Uh because now that
that says okay if this is truly an
automated process, it's improving, it's
getting better even as it's collecting
useful experience. Now I can take it and
I can put it in lots of different
domains, collect useful experience, do
something that people actually want and
it'll improve the model. So that I think
is a really major step uh on that road.
I think another really major step is to
demonstrate a very concrete and
practically useful way to transfer
knowledge to transfer common sense to
achieve robustness. So that's like the u
kind of the the other scenario where you
don't get to practice. If you're driving
your car on the road and you see a fire
truck and you see like a bunch of
traffic cones, even if you've never been
in that situation before, like your
common sense tells you like, "Hey, I
should like slow down." like what what
maybe I don't know how to react
optimally, but I shouldn't just like
barrel on through the cones and like you
know uh upset the firefighters and so
on. Like so that's common sense. And if
you can apply that common sense to
effectively recover from unexpected
situations like when the robot put the
spatula in the oven like you know it
should probably open it up, take it out
like it knows that this is not the thing
you do semantically. That I think is
like another important step because that
tells us that we can use common sense to
fix mistakes. I could imagine um a more
narrowly scoped robot. Let's say it's a
humanoid robot. That's one step in
assembly line in manufacturing. In my
understanding, you're less interested in
that because that's not really a step
towards that general intelligence. What
I would say, it's not that I'm less
interested in it. It's that um I think
that the real world has these leaky
abstractions that make that kind of
stuff a lot more complex than it seems.
Um let me try to explain this with an
analogy. So in the in the '9s um when
people were like really started working
uh kind of full steam on autonomous
driving, there was this idea that we
could avoid a lot of the hard problems
by kind of instrumenting the environment
a little bit. like we'll have like
magnetic sensors along the highway and
so on. And cars will have like a little
uh you know uh sensor on them and a
little um transmitter so they can tell
where each of the cars are. Kind of like
the way you do it with aircraft
basically. Uh and then people thought
well we don't really need like fancy AI.
We'll just like have these sensors and
and it'll just work. And that just
basically didn't go anywhere because the
real world has so many messy exceptions
and special cases that even if 99% of
the time like the magnetic sensors and
all that stuff just allow the car to
drive, the 1% when like someone steps in
the middle of the road or there's like a
piece of trash or whatever, it just
messes everything up. So the thing that
actually worked was when said like,
"Hey, we're going to not try to avoid
the hard problem. we're going to
actually try to deploy our cars not in
like middle of nowhere but in San
Francisco like very messy and let's just
let's just deal with it head-on and that
allowed the that community to make
progress and I think robotic
manipulation is going to be the same way
that that um past the fully structured
world of the factory if you want to go
even a little bit outside of that even
if 99% of the time it's all like pretty
straightforward that 1% when something
weird happens means that you really need
to the full scope of the problem
basically to be addressed. This kind of
reminds me I remember Figure had this
demo where they live streamed the robot
kind of sorting packages when you
watched that demo. Is that a did is does
it demonstrate generalization in your
opinion?
>> Yeah. Yeah, I think it does. And by the
way, this is something that I find very
encouraging is that like I mentioned
that it's hard to show generalization in
a video. And it's clear that lots of
people are thinking about that and that
are thinking about how do you like how
do you present something that that
somebody can watch and take in kind of
at a glance what generalization is. I
think you can see a lot of creative
steps towards that. Live demos, these
kind of like really long time lapses. I
think it's a great idea and I think
that's a like a a really nice way to
move towards elevating the importance of
generalization in people's kind of
conscious consciousness. Um you know we
um when we were working on the um the PI
star 6 project the RL project that we
did uh late last year we um wanted to do
some longer uh horizon experiments. In
some case it's obvious like we had our
robot assembling boxes at at Dandelion
Chocolate Factory. So they're like, you
know, it's an actual chocolate factory,
so they need the boxes. So we run it for
several days. Uh but we had this coffee
task which was uh the robot was using an
espresso machine to make espresso. So
what we did is we ran it for 13 hours
making espresso drinks. Uh and we are,
you know, we tried to be like very uh I
guess um environmentally conscious about
this. So we didn't want to like throw
out the coffee. So after 13 hours,
everyone in the office was like a little
wiry cuz someone has to like drink the
coffee. But it like it ran for 13 hours
and it was pretty cool. But it it
screwed up a few times. Like it'll um
spill all the the coffee grounds and
then it needs to go and get like a cloth
and wipe it down. But like it does it
and it's you know nothing exploded 13
hours went by. Probably the most
negative consequence was like loss of
sleep from too much caffeination.
>> But when it spills the coffee grounds
and cleans it up is that's it did that
by itself.
>> Well, so the way the way that that
experiment was done is that there is a
high level prompting. So like roughly
the prompt is updated maybe every like
uh 5 minutes or so like in between
semantically coherent tasks. So you tell
it like make espresso, clean up the
machine etc. So those steps the actual
like clean up the the machine was
commanded by a person. Um in principle
we could automate that. In fact one of
the things we're spending a lot of
effort now is improving our high level
policy that does those commands. But for
that experiment yeah like every 5
minutes somebody basically updates what
is being asked to do. Like the way we
intended it was like the commands would
be like if you go to to an actual coffee
shop, you say like, "Oh, I want a latte.
I want an espresso." Like that was
supposed to be the prompt. Except then
you also have to tell it, "I want you to
clean it up before you do the next one."
[laughter]
>> That makes sense. Open AAI, Enthropic,
Cursor, and Versel all use this product
to make their lives better. And the
problem it solves is when you're
building SAS or an AI product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSO, there's SKIM, there's
arbback, there's audit logs. These are
all things that take time to integrate
but aren't the main focus of your app.
Work OS is an API layer that lets you
meet all of these requirements in just a
few lines of code. So, let's say you
have a new SAS product and you want to
sell to other companies. Work OS will
solve all of these critical feature gaps
for you. You can check them out at
workos.com to learn more and get
started. and I appreciate them for
supporting my work and sponsoring this
podcast. It sounds like on the way to
generalizing
uh data is a very important part of that
and I was reading there's different
types of data there's simulated data you
could uh collect like physical
interactive data and I wanted to hear
your take on what's the best data to get
what's the worst and what are the pros
and cons. Uh this is by the way like a
question that is uh I guess quite like
there's a lot of discussion in the
robotics community about this question
and some people have like very opposite
opinions on it. My own take on this is
that um a lot of different data sources
are easier for the model to internalize
if it can ground them in a thorough
physical understanding of the world. So
uh let me try to explain what I mean
with like a few examples. Um, if you
want to learn to fly an airplane, you
will probably use a a simulator, at
least during part of your training. Uh,
but the simulator makes a lot of sense
to you because when you start using the
simulator, you have a lot of world
knowledge that you can use to ground
what's going on. Like you know that when
you uh are using the flight simulator to
learn how to fly the airplane, you're
not just like playing a video game.
You're trying to acquire knowledge that
will then that you will then use with a
real airplane. and you understand that
there's sort of an abstraction there.
Same thing if you um uh if you're
playing like a really cartoony like you
know Atari game or something right like
you know that all the symbols on the
screen you can sort of connect them to
things that you've experienced in your
life and you can make an analogy there.
So, a lot of that, like even though it
kind of seems like these simulated
environments reflect aspects of the real
world, to us, they make a lot of sense
because we kind of bring to bear a lot
of our own prior experience and we fill
in the blanks that that the that the
that the simulation has. Um, and also if
you if you want to use uh data uh you
yourself as a person of somebody else
doing something, if you you watch
someone uh let's say cooking a meal,
right? Um, even though you don't
experience every movement they're
experiencing, you have a lot of that
knowledge that you bring to bear and
you're like, "Okay, I see they're
picking up the salt shaker. Like, I've
put salt on things before, so I kind of
roughly know what's going on there." And
I can file it away at this level
abstraction of like add salt without
having to like figure out all their
muscle movements. So my point with this
is that once you have that understanding
of how you do things physically with
your own body and how you experience the
physical world, now all these other
sources of knowledge can be connected up
to it because that foundation you get
from your experience helps you ground
everything. So where I'm going with this
is that if we have a robotic foundation
model that is trained on lots of real
embodied data that provides that
grounding, it might actually be much
better able to absorb other sources of
knowledge. And this is actually like a
little bit upside down relative to how
some people think about it because it's
very tempting looking at the success of
like internet data for LLMs to say well
maybe we should do the opposite. Maybe
we should like start with like YouTube
videos and then put robot data on top of
that. But I think it's actually the
other way around. And I actually I even
have like a little bit of evidence for
this. So my um my colleague uh sir Saraj
together with um uh Simar from Georgia
Tech they had a project together uh a
while back where they took our robot
foundation model and they added human
video data but they they didn't start
with human video data. They actually
started with a model train on robot data
and then added video data on top of it.
And what they did is they looked at the
representations inside the model. Uh
basically how does the model represent
human experience versus robot
experience? And they found that if you
use a small model with a small amount of
robot data, predictably the human
experience and the robot experience are
fully separated. Meaning that the
feature representations are different.
But if you train on lots of robot data
from lots of different robots, then the
features are grouped much more by what
task is being done rather than by
whether it's a human or a robot. And
like when we looked at the feature
plots, it was just like mindboggling
because we literally when you when you
crank up the amount of robot data to
100%, they just line up perfectly. like
you you see the you know you do this TC
embedding you see the shapes of the
embeddings and it's just all task
identity and like minimal sensitivity to
embodiment and to me that's kind of
mind-blowing because like this the base
model wasn't trained on any human data
at all but once you start adding human
data it represents it exactly the same
way and I think that's really exciting
and I think that that to me is like one
one of the strongest indicators that if
you have that good foundation of robot
experience you can put everything else
on top of it and it's actually better at
absorbing that
>> is it important that that base model has
data that was collected using that
specific set of motors, specific set of
joints. So far, we've uh obviously put a
lot of effort into cross embodyment
models that can handle many different
robot types, but generally you do need
data of the robot you're going to be
deploying on to get good performance. Uh
so kind of the metric of uh of
generalization there is not can you zero
shot a new robot but it's mostly can you
get away with less experience from the
new robot and transfer skills from other
robots. Okay so that's the current state
of things. Now there is a little bit of
a kind of surprisingly positive read on
that which is even though you need data
from these robots um the amount of
special stuff that the model is doing is
uh kind of minimal. Like when we started
doing all of this, I had like a big long
list of all the cool research I wanted
to do to better accommodate different
morphologies like can you like
factoriize the model's representation in
some way so that there's like a you know
a six degree of freedom arm head and a
seven degree head and a gripper head
etc. We didn't do any of that like we
the model just outputs like a big vector
of numbers. Uh if the robot has less
degrees of freedom than the number it
outputs it just zero pads it. There's
just like nothing fancy. Uh and that's
it. and then it just train on all the
robots and outputs the correct actions
based on what is seeing through the
camera essentially.
But now to to your point about whether
you can uh handle new robots. Um so so
far the thing that we focused on and I
think this is showing some promise is to
be able to transfer skills between
robots and this is actually where
the um particular choices in how the
model works uh seem to matter. Um for
example uh you can have a model that
does some intermediate thinking and that
thinking can be done in different
modalities. So you can think in text and
thinking in text is really good for
transferring um highle behavioral
structure. So that's basically how you
understand that hey if I want to like
clean the kitchen and put away like the
silverware first open the drawer like
that's kind of a semantic inference and
you can transfer that uh very well
because obviously that's like largely
agnostic to any embodiment or anything
like that. But even lower level things
can be transferred if you use the right
representation. So one experiment we did
is we had a a thinking stage that is
expressed in images where you basically
like dream up an image of the next
milestone in the task. And with that, we
could actually get um a robot, the UR5
robot to fold a t-shirt, even though we
didn't have any t-shirt folding data on
the UR5 because while getting the the
the arm motions correct is very hard
because the robot basically requires
very different joint angles to do the
task, uh cooking up an image of what it
looks like for it to fold a shirt is not
that hard because like you've seen the
robot arm in all sorts of different
poses. You've seen the shirt in all
different stages of being folded and
unfolded. You know roughly where it
should hold it. So getting a good
generative model to cook up that image
is pretty straightforward. And once you
have the image then from that backing
out the correct actions is easy too
because you can just look at the
synthesized arm angle and just like back
out what the angle should be. So it it's
it's not changing the problem but it's
just introducing this intermediate step
that makes it easier to solve. Just like
if you're solving a math problem if you
figure out like the right intermediate
step kind of the answer is obvious from
that intermediate step. And I think
that's really exciting because now now
that shows that this level of
generalization across robots and I'm
sure other generalization too can be
facilitated with thinking just like an
LLMs but with a twist. You have to think
in the right modality.
>> Interesting. So it it outputs a I guess
that image is what its video sensor is
seeing and it's like the next step.
>> Yeah. You can almost think of it like
image editing. You can do the same thing
with video. You can do it with video
prediction. But the key is to like
imagine what it would look like to
progress on this task. Like that seems
like a very human thing to do, right?
You know, some things you can you you
plan semantically and some things you
plan spatially. Like if you're doing
rock climbing, you're probably not
thinking like, hey, left arm to rock 37
cm to the left. You're probably more
like imagining your arm reaching for the
rock. Earlier in the conversation, you
mentioned that Whimo was very inspiring
and um you know their kind of path to
productionization is proof that you can
do real world generalized robotics. And
if I recall correctly when I was, you
know, a lot younger, it was kind of this
early promise of this is going to happen
and then in reality it took a lot
longer. And so I guess my question is in
the case of humanoid robotics,
what would make you say singledigit
years it's coming versus a long tail and
you know policy challenges as well. I
could imagine.
>> I think one big difference between how
robotic foundation models address the
problem and how more traditional
engineered systems address the problem
is that the stack is really thin. So
it's not easy to train a foundation
model. You need to uh obviously you need
to get the right data. There's a lot of
work that goes into curating, labeling,
all that other kind of stuff. But the
actual software that runs on the robot
is very very simple. Uh so uh you know
you might have some kind of thinking or
reasoning stage. You might have uh you
might have the model produce actions. It
needs to be fast enough. But the like
just if you think about in terms of raw
lines of code, it's much much lower than
a more traditional AV stack. Uh and you
know, partly that's because modern
autonomous vehicles, the work on that
started a lot earlier with very
different technologies and evolved over
time. Partly it's also because the
problem is more safety critical. Like
yes, you don't want uh a robotic
manipulator to like drop a fragile
object, but at the end of the day,
that's a lot less bad than having a car
hit somebody. So that is not to say that
the safety challenges with robots are uh
are not real. They're very real and it's
very important to tackle them. In fact,
it's probably one of the harder ends of
the problem. But they are not as much of
a hard stop to practical deployments
because you can come up with tasks and
environments and domains and also
physical hardware where those problems
are a lot less uh severe. So uh I think
that that that combination radically
simpler software stack plus uh less uh
drastic software challenges I think
actually make it a lot easier and
because you know to your earlier point
uh that there is this kind of flywheel
effect that there's a positive feedback
loop that uh you know starting to get
things out in the world even under some
constraints will actually facilitate
getting them out more and more. I think
a lot of people are familiar with this
idea of a post-mortem,
you know, looking back on why something
failed. But in this case, I'm curious,
what would you say to a a premortem? And
in the sense of if humanoid robotics did
not succeed in single-digit years, what
do you think would be the most likely
reason why humanoid robotics failed?
Ultimately, for these things to to be
truly useful, they do need to reach a
level of reliability and robustness and
generalization that is higher than what
we typically expect from LLMs for
example uh or uh you know generative AI
for like images and video because
typically like these tools they are very
much human interactive tools like you
you get an LLM to do something and it
doesn't do quite what you want so you
sort of revise your prompt and you you
basically like you iterate with it and
and that's why like even the earlier um
LM tools like the first version of Chad
GPT, even though they were much more
primitive than what we have now, they
were still already useful because
somebody could just like keep hammering
out until it it basically solves their
problem. You know, just like if if
you're using a search engine, like you
type something into the search engine,
you don't get quite what you want. You
revise your query and then you get what
you want. Whereas with a robot, like the
the full value of it is unlocked when
it's actually doing the thing
autonomously. So it's it's having to
have somebody like constantly iterate
for every single task is almost like
antithetical to the benefit that you're
getting. So I think a lot of the risk
has to do with how easy is it to get
that level of reliability and
robustness. And that's again where some
of the demos might be like a little bit
misleading because if someone shows a
demo of the robot doing something cool I
mean you know obviously if if everything
is presented in a forthright way that's
that could still be very good indicator
of progress but it doesn't make it
obvious how far or how close it is to
reaching that practically relevant level
of robustness. So, I'm personally a big
believer in uh using uh techniques like
reinforcement learning that can actually
benefit from autonomous experience to
kind of fine-tune that last few
percentage points to make it go from
like 95 to actually 100%. But that's
really important and it's not yet a
solved problem.
>> If it did take longer than expected,
it's because the bar is higher. because
the bar is higher and in particular like
those last few uh the kind of the last
inch so to speak is something that
requires not just really good models but
also new innovations in technology. I
mean I don't think that you know I'm not
the kind of person that would say like
oh we should like throw out everything
that we know about foundation models and
start over. I don't think it's that at
all. I think that roughly the puzzle
pieces that we have are actually very
good puzzle pieces. But still we should
acknowledge that right now the methods
and the models need more work to cross
that level of robustness.
>> In LLMs it feels like everyone is doing
kind of the same thing but different
flavors in the robotics industry. Is it
is everyone doing kind of the same
thing? Are there any hottake
architectures that are different
direction? I actually think that there's
a lot more heterogeneity than it might
seem. Um, one big dividing line that I
think is maybe not as obvious uh from
just kind of looking at the results is
the distinction between kind of fully
embracing the foundation model ethos so
to speak versus uh focusing on spec
specific like kind of vertical areas.
And I think this is like kind of hard to
tease out sometimes because obviously
like you know everyone's going to say
like oh I'm doing the thing that LM did
like because like that's the cool thing
but you know the foundational model
ethos fundamentally is something like
this that if you have a particular
problem you want to solve it is better
to train a more general model that can
use data from a breadth of problems and
if you do it right it'll actually be
better at the specialized problem you
want to solve than a narrow specialist.
So you know to again to come back to the
LM analogy if you want to do machine
translation don't build a machine
translation system build a language
model that understands all language
tasks and then throw it at machine
translation
and in robotics I think that is like
actually very deeply uncomfortable to
people because if someone is actually
like working on an application like
they're doing like warehouse automation
it is very awkward to then to to like
think like oh if I want to do warehouse
automation let me like collect data of
like putting away silverware in
kitchens. It just it just sounds
bizarre. But that is the foundation
model lesson that if you have enough
breadth, if you collect data from a wide
range of different tasks, then you will
acquire those generalizable skills and
if your model is is is built correctly,
it will repurpose those skills for
whatever situation it encounters. So I
think it is actually true that if even
if you want to build a warehousing
robot, you're better off collecting a
breath of data and will be better at
handling all the weird edge cases you
might encounter even in that warehouse
domain. But this is not something that's
easy for people to accept because it's
just so like antithetical to the uh
principle of building kind of a a
traditional vertically integrated
robotic system.
>> I noticed this this uh new interesting
phenomenon with these AI companies which
is if they are wildly successful it
creates this um I guess worry or new set
of things. So for instance when
enthropic became had a very powerful
model then the government comes in and
there's these you know worries about
safety and and risk and all that and I'm
I'm curious how you think about that
like if if physical intelligence this
year had a phenomenal incredibly capable
generalized model how do you think about
those kinds of topics that might come up
>> working on AI safety is not a new uh my
my colleague at UC Berkeley Stuart
Russell was talking about this stuff
like over a decade ago and lots of
people spent a lot of time working on
it. It's just that the trouble is when
the technology moves so fast the
important problems are not just a
function of like you know the core
principles it's also a function of how
society reacts to it what kind of tools
are adopted and so on um and I think
that's very very hard to anticipate so
um I don't have like a very satisfying
answer here in terms of how we are
approaching it our philosophy around all
this stuff is
basically one of empirical
experimentation like let's get stuff out
there. Let's see what happens in the
real world. Let's see what goes right
and what goes wrong so that we have as
much of a preview for you know what the
technology can do, what are its
weaknesses, what are its strengths uh
and and so on. But you know at the end
of the day you kind of have to just like
keep your eyes open, see what happens
and adjust as you go. It's it's very
hard to anticipate. And you know, I
think your question though is very
spoton even though I don't have a great
answer for you because like yeah, if
we're having like this much um concern
and and uh issues with AI systems that
are basically limited to using
computers, we're presumably going to
have strictly more concerns and issues
with AI systems that can do everything
in the physical world that we can do,
right? So the issues are real. It's
just, you know, you kind of have to like
see what happens and then adjust. And
that's kind of in the the scary path.
But in the in the happy path, if
everything goes well and we have
incredibly capable models and uh robots
in 10 years, is the north star that
that's the end of human labor. I believe
it's a mistake to think of robots as
mechanical people, right? like um you
know computers at some level are kind of
like mechanical brains but when personal
computers like really took off in the
'9s early 2000s etc. It's not like the
first thing that happened is that you
know people replaced their brains with
computers rather what we saw is actually
a proliferation of very different kinds
of computers. We saw kind of like uh
ubiquitous computing. So you would have
a computer on your desk but you might
also have one in your pocket. You might
have one in your refrigerator and in
your car like because computing became
so accessible, you could have a little
bit of computing in everything. And you
know, I don't think that that's what
like the the people that first started
thinking about this stuff in the 40s and
50s would have imagined. They would have
imagined like, you know, roomsiz
computers that whose job it is to like
control the the the you know, the policy
of an entire country or something rather
than like a little bit of computer in
everybody's refrigerator. So I think
it's it's you know by analogy of that we
might imagine there might be like a
little bit of physical actuation in
everything and it might just be like
lots of everyday things that you have to
do yourself now you get like a little
bit of help with it. I think the other
example that's worth thinking about is
um modern coding agents, right? So I I
think that you know this is something
where of course the jury is still out as
to what the endgame of coding agents is,
but certainly uh from the experience of
uh software engineers today. Like it
kind of seems like probably fair to say
that most would consider coding agents
to be more empowering them rather than
like uh you know uh somehow causing them
to have a panic. I mean, obviously some
people might might have a panic, but in
general, at least from the software
engineers that that I've talked to and
from my own experience, it's more
empowering to have to kind of be able to
amplify how much work you can do uh with
AI tools. So, I think from that and and
that maybe is like a pretty direct
analogy because that is straight up an
example of an actual real job where AI
has entered into it and has actually
provided more leverage to people doing
that job. So I think that's another
example that we can look to but you know
the truth is that I think it remains to
be seen.
>> So in in LLM's there's a few seinal
papers that if you read those papers you
kind of get a sense of the lineage of
the breakthroughs that mattered and
understanding where we are today in the
robotics industry. Are there a set of
top papers that you really think kind of
show the breakthroughs that people
should know about if they're curious
about the state-of-the-art in terms of
uh humanoid robotics? One thing I would
point out um uh and this is like partly
a shameless plug because I am a
co-author on that paper though candidly
like uh like 99.9% of the work on this
was done by by um Tony who was lead
author is the uh the original ACT paper
the Aloha paper. It's kind it's an
interesting example because in some ways
the ideas weren't really that new but
they were illustrated in a really nice
way and the idea was that hey um if you
set up the right kind of lowcost robot
setup in in his case it was based on um
these robot arms from Trusson Robotics
that they're like $7,000 hobbyist arms.
He set them up in a banual setup with a
leader follower to the operation device.
And he showed that actually if you do it
right without really any particularly
fancy tricks, you could easily collect
the operation data of extremely dextrous
tasks that people had previously thought
would require like very sophisticated
hardware and all sorts of like really
expensive stuff and then set up like a
fairly
straightforward transformer-based model
and it could actually do a lot of those
tasks. And it's kind of like an
interesting thing because usually in
academic research we put a big premium
on like you know do you have some like
sophisticated new mathematical thing or
some sophisticated like uh technical
insight and in that paper which I think
at this point has been hugely
influential. The insight is really just
like yeah just put together the right
pieces and have a little bit more faith
in what a simple robot could do so to
speak equipped with a good intent
learning system. and he showed like
things like um uh replacing batteries in
a remote control. Uh he even had he even
got like a little like a mannequin foot
and he showed that you could put a shoe
on it like for like an assistive task
sort of like you know some some people
need help getting their shoes on so
that's good. Um but like what what
people find found I think so interesting
about that paper is just how far you
could get with like relatively simple
building blocks. And at this point the
the a like he he open sourced the code
for it and the act code has been used by
like lots of people sort of like if
someone wants a very basic starter kit
for like robotic learning that's usually
what they grab and I think that it's
worth for somebody who wants to get into
the field to go through that paper and
really understand what's going on there
because even though in some ways it's
not that sophisticated
I think it provides like a bit of
calibration on what matters right like
you know the details matter But the
details don't have to be complicated.
>> Before all this uh large model robotics
kind of uh wave prior to that um Boston
Dynamics had these really impressive
demonstrations and tons of um mind
share. I guess I wasn't even in the
field by saying wow they're really doing
incredible robotics. And then in the
last I don't know how many years I don't
really hear about them much anymore. Um
is there some shift in the industry that
made that so or you know is that
something you could explain?
>> So the way I would explain it is this
that um there are you know robotics
at at some level is about building
complex systems. So um even though it
kind of it's very tempting to say like
oh there's different areas of AI there's
like LLMs and vision and robotics one of
those is not like the others because for
robots you actually need like all the
parts everything from like how you you
know uh how you wire up the robot what
the power source is what does the
actuator look like all the way to how
does it do like high level planning to
determine like what task to do next and
even though it's kind even though we
could look at these things and say like
oh all of these different videos and
different companies and different demos.
They're all robotics. They're really
kind of a different parts of the stack.
Um,
a lot of what the classic Boston
Dynamics results show is um, very
sophisticated hardware, very carefully
designed hardware with a uh, traditional
control approach with very smart
controls engineers setting everything
up, but with comparatively less emphasis
on the kind of decision-m aspect and I
think that there, you know, at a
particular point in time that actually
made a lot of sense because we can't
build the physical body like it doesn't
matter what kind of decision making
system is running on it. Um
but uh to our earlier discussion about
generalization,
you know, at this point we're at a stage
in the development of these things that
even though we can do more on hardware,
in many ways it's good enough. And the
big challenge is how to have the
decision-making loop that actually works
and that reacts intelligently to
everything in the environment. And the
way and the place where I would draw the
the dividing line between those is
it's like decision-m loop doesn't mean
symbolic decisions. It could mean
low-level decisions. The question is do
you need to take the rest of the
environment into account or are you just
dealing with the robot? So if you want
to do a backflip on flat ground, you
most have to deal with the robot. But if
you want to pick up a coffee cup off of
a table, even though that's maybe in
some ways simpler than doing a backflip,
you really have to understand what's
going on in the rest of the world rather
than just your own body. And that
dividing line, I think the way the
technology has panned out, I think it's
fair to say that that is the dividing
line between AI and controls. Like
controls is when you have to control the
robot body. AI is when you have to take
into account what goes on outside of the
robot.
and and and I think that that's why you
see this divide because I think a lot of
the demos where you mostly needed to
deal with the robot itself and not the
rest of the world really good controls
could allow you to could admit a very
good solution there a and you know
another thing I would say here is like
okay if there's a lot of controls work
that goes into doing some particular
skill well there is actually something
to learn from that because if you can
handdesign a controller that performs a
sophisticated behavior very likely you
can also learn that controller. So like
just that proof of existence that the
thing is possible and not only possible
but also simple enough that a person
could build it because remember people
are you know at the end of the day even
even with code these days the kind of
complexity that people can handle is not
as high as the kind of complexity the AI
can handle. So if a person can
handdesign something uh to do a backflip
or do some acrobatics that's a really
great proof of existence that there
exists some relatively parsimmonious
control law for doing that skill and
parsimonious does mean generalizable. So
if it's simple enough for a person to
design, probably there's something
fairly general in there and if you can
learn it uh and automate it without
having to have the human controls
engineers in the loop, that's that's
good news.
>> And then last question for you is you if
you could go back to when you just
entered the industry and give yourself
some advice knowing everything you know
now, what would you say?
One thing that I've learned uh over the
last uh few years um which I think is a
little different than kind of my
original mindset is I think that
addressing robotics effectively requires
using um very broad prior knowledge. And
I think that there there's this idea
that a lot of people in robotic learning
have which I think I I shared initially
that you know since people learn things
kind of from scratch maybe robots should
learn things from scratch too. Um so uh
like for example uh in um some of our
early work on large scale robotic
learning at Google we uh we had this uh
what we call the the arm farm project
like we set up a bunch of robot arms in
a in a conference room actually because
we didn't have a proper lab but it was a
conference room and we had them all like
grasping objects and the idea was well
if they grasp like millions of objects
they'll learn very general like grasping
strategies and it basically worked like
they could learn to grasp objects but it
was very hard to like take get further
from that to the next level. So, okay,
now I can pick up anything, but like so
what? Uh can like it it didn't serve as
a very good stepping stone for more
complex skills. And I think part of that
was that we were approaching this like
very blank slate like let's start from
zero and see if knowing nothing in
advance the robot could start picking up
behaviors. But I think that it's much
much more practical to get all this to
work if you can combine robot experience
with knowledge that you can pull in from
other sources. Like for example, I was
very skeptical initially about the
utility of language and I think
scientifically this is defensible which
is that like hey um you know like
animals can do some pretty impressive
things like monkeys can do really cool
stuff but monkeys as far as I know can't
speak at least not very eloquently um so
maybe our robots should also be able to
do stuff and they don't necessarily need
to understand language but I think the
subtlety there is what's important is
not language it's it's
prior knowledge that you can put in as a
scaffold on your learning process. And
you can pull in that knowledge in all
sorts of ways. Like, you know, humans
don't necessarily pull that in entirely
through language. Humans all and monkeys
certainly don't. Uh they do it from
observation, from observing other
people, other creatures and so on. So,
there's lots of sources of prior
knowledge. But the point is that you got
to get that prior knowledge in there.
Otherwise, you're actually faced with a
harder problem than what humans and
animals have to solve. Because like, you
know, if a person had to figure out how
to like assemble IKEA furniture, but
they've never actually encountered any
article of furniture in their entire
life, like [laughter]
okay, that would be like pretty
difficult because they don't even know
what like what the point of this is or
what the the endgame looks like. Uh so
yeah, prior knowledge is important. And
while I'm still a big fan of learning
things through experience, I think that,
you know, my advice to myself would have
been take prior knowledge more
seriously.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, Sergey. I really appreciate
it.
>> Yeah, thank you for your questions. Hey,
thank you for watching this podcast. If
you liked it and you want to see the
show grow, please support with a comment
or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskov, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. This is in the case,
but yeah, we launched on Kickstarter and
we hit our goal within eight hours of
launching. I really appreciate it if you
were one of the people who grabbed one
of the early units. Um, we're now
working on the long journey of building
the tooling now. And so, if you still
want to pick one up, I've left the late
pledges open on Kickstarter, so you can
grab one there. I'll put a link in the
description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast and I'll see you in
the next